Guide to the Franklin Edgerton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Franklin Edgerton papers
1926-1964
1938-1961
MS 1720
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The papers consist of biographical information in the form of a eulogy; drafts of articles; reprints of published works; and miscellaneous files.
Edgerton, Franklin, 1885-1963
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Franklin Edgerton was born on July 24, 1885 in Lemars, Iowa. He received a B.A. from Cornell University in 1905. From 1906 to 1909, he did graduate work at Johns Hopkins University; and served successively as assistant professor, professor, and Johnston scholar in Sanskrit and comparative philology from 1909 to 1913. He was assistant professor (1913-1925) and professor (1926) of Sanskrit at the University of Pennsylvania. In 1926 he became Salisbury Professor of Sanskrit and Comparative Philology at Yale University. In 1953 he wrote the Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar and Dictionary, and earned the status of professor emeritus. From 1953 to 1954 Edgerton was a visiting professor of Indology at Banaras Hindu University; and in 1956 he was a state guest of the Indian government for the 2500th anniversary of the Buddha's death. A noted Sanskritist and linguistic scholar, he was a founding member of the Linguistic Society of America, and was elected president in 1934. He was the author of over 200 works. Edgerton died on December 7, 1963.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of biographical information in the form of a eulogy; drafts of articles; reprints of published works; and miscellaneous files.
Indologists; Sanskritists; Edgerton, Franklin, 1885-1963; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Biography/eulogy, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Writings
    - Drafts/typescripts
      - "The Buddha and Metaphysics" [typescript], 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Notes on Tagore's Educational Philosophy" [typescript], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "A Composite Indian Portrait: Buddha, Asoka, Gandhi" [drafts], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Asoka, Buddhist Emperor of India" [draft], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Reprints
      - "Etymology and Interpretation", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Dominant Ideas in the Formation of Indian Culture", 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Sanskrit Historical Phonology", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "The Buddha and the Language", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "The Hour of Death", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1926-1927, 1954, 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)